There's this brilliant KFC ad.
>> Welcome to Chicken Town.
Home of the imitators.
Because when [music] you're on top,
everybody wants a piece of you.
>> And lately, we've been feeling a lot
like KFC.
There's this thumbnail, this one, this
What even is this? Every thumbnail
[music] we invent, every title we
construct, every animation we build,
sometimes entire videos.
Countless AI slop channels relentlessly
copy us. And one day we decided
enough is enough.
So we investigated. We looked into these
[music] channels and found who's likely
behind them. We joined a Discord
community, paid 75 bucks for a coaching,
and subjected our fact-checking team to
an unhealthy amount of AI misinformation
spread to hundreds of thousands of
people on topics like, well, the
Holocaust. Because all of this is
endangering educational content on
YouTube. It's damaging for everyone in
our niche.
It undermines trust in journalism. And
really, it's just so annoying.
>> They think that my voice is AI. They
even think that my face is AI generated.
>> The cost of production has gone down
tremendously.
>> This is a new form of industrialized
plagiarism and creative theft.
>> True crime, video essays, science, no
specs is safe. We're in the golden era
of soulless slop.
>> I think a couple of years ago, a 3D
thumbnail was associated to good quality
content, but now it's perceived as AI
slop.
>> There's no wish to make something
creative. It's just a get-rich scheme.
>> [music]
>> AI is undoubtedly useful in many aspects
of life and it's here to stay. We use AI
tools selectively in our own
organization, for example, to organize
and skim through our research.
>> [music]
>> In rare cases, we use generated imagery
as a basis for compositions in Photoshop
if no comparable stock images are
available. But, the rise of specifically
generative AI has also made it very easy
to mass-produce content. There's AI
music on Spotify, terrible AI recipes
and home decor on Pinterest. Boomers are
losing their mind on Facebook.
>> This is another account that I found
that posts images like this. It always
seems to be a child sculpting something
very impressive out of trash. And the
people in the comments just eat this
stuff up, dude. Great work. Keep it up.
Great talent. Nice one. Thanks.
>> But, one platform especially has [music]
become a dumping ground for AI slop.
More than 20% of the videos YouTube's
algorithm shows to new users may now be
slop.
>> The cost of production has gone down
tremendously. You can have content which
is not so good or or or reasonable in
quality, which is not competing against
something which is generated by a human
who has spent a lot of time and
investment and invested in the little
acquiring skills.
>> This is Dr. Akil Boatswain. He's an
associate professor at the University of
Bath School of Management.
>> And then you have this thing which can
generate precisely that at a very low
cost. And they both compete.
>> There's something genuinely frustrating
about clicking on a video and then
realizing it's just another AI voice
reading an AI script feeding you AI
visuals.
And we reached a full circle moment when
we came across this video about the
invasion of AI slop made with AI.
The only comment reads, "Oh God, this
video is AI, too." The creator gave it a
heart.
>> [music]
>> And it's moments like these that make
you believe the internet is really dead.
Around 100 people work on Fern, our
German channel and our German podcast.
>> [music]
>> A dedicated team of journalists, art
directors, producers, 2D and 3D
animators, and fact-checkers, all to
bring you that weekly dose of something
to watch during lunch. But now, [music]
thanks to the power of AI, you can be
Fern, too. You can wear our skin and
talk in our voice and walk in our shoes.
>> So, I'll take screenshots from Fern's
video, paste them into ChatGPT, and
simply say, "Regenerate this photo."
>> Most people think [music] you need to be
professional 3D designer with years of
experience to create videos like this.
Well, they're dead wrong. I've cracked
the code
>> He uses a Fern idea generator, a Fern
script writer, and a Fern image
generator.
>> It's literally identical to what Fern
uses, and I would dare to say that ours
could be even better than what Fern is
using here as an example.
>> And the best part, you don't have to be
good at literally anything anymore.
>> You see, I don't have that budget
available to me. Neither do I have the
skills to animate, do academic [music]
research, or I have that smooth
voiceover. But I do know how to use AI.
>> Some of it is just outrageous
misinformation.
>> You've probably seen channels like Fern
on YouTube, where everything looks like
it came out of Blender. And when you
first see it, you probably think that
everyone spent weeks building [music] it
inside Blender. And they actually
didn't.
>> Um
>> We actually did. And it just doesn't
end.
Yikes.
Imitation is flattery, we get that.
We've been inspired by the greats on
this platform all our career. But to us,
there's a difference between countless
hours in After Effects to recreate Vox
style maps and asking a machine to just
clone something. We get why they choose
to copy our work. Edutainment is a good
niche to target for slop gods. Channels
are often faceless, a version of the
animations are now replicable with AI,
and people like you learn a little
something while binging down a hot
pocket. The thumbnails don't rely on the
creator's face, so you can fool people
into thinking any considerable effort
went into whatever your chain of tools
spit out. So of course, we're not the
only edutainment channel having to deal
with this.
>> So when I started making videos, I very
much built my channel around 3D
animations and high-quality visuals. And
a few years ago, I think that was very
unique and there wasn't a lot of that
out there. But now, that very style that
I based my channel off has become kind
of synonymous with AI slop. And that's a
challenge for me.
>> What I've noticed is that several people
in my audience look at my 3D style of
thumbnails and they associate them to
low-effort [music] content.
And my videos take a couple months to
research and produce, so I'm struggling
a bit to convey that in the thumbnail,
uh, while keeping it attractive enough
to get clicks.
>> I've seen videos take inspiration from
my visual style before, which is fine,
by the way. But this was very different.
These visuals weren't just recreated in
some animation software to look like
mine.
>> [music]
>> They were literally the same scenes with
just a few things changed.
>> There's even math slop, which is just oh
god. Imagine trying to actually learn
something on YouTube like it's 2017.
Especially our thumbnails get ripped a
lot and slightly changed by slop
channels, likely using AI. So we thought
it would be funny to use AI to find
matches. Yannick, our data guy, because
we actually have talented humans working
here, set up a program to identify cases
[music] in which our thumbnails get
lifted. And there are so, so many.
We confronted several of the creators of
these tutorials. Some took down their
videos afterward. Others explained that
they didn't earn money from their
tutorials, and others considered the
tutorials free marketing for us. One
creator said it clearly, he just wanted
to make money and had only briefly used
Fernan as an example.
With regards to We Are Fernan at Home,
one AI channel stands out in particular,
Loom.
It's part of Loom Studio, a network of
three channels, Loom, Rocks, and Aigo.
In total, they have more than 300,000
subscribers. Aigo and Loom seem to
generate quite some revenue. These
channels regularly appropriate our
thumbnails. They rip them and then
likely let AI change or add elements.
But sometimes they also seem to simply
copy and recreate full videos of ours
like this one. Some of their content
gets over a million views. They also
seem to take from others like Mr. Beast.
In many thumbnails, Mr. Beast gets
replaced with a 3D character. In one
instance, a video with such a thumbnail
got over 2 million views.
That could equate to $11,000 in revenue.
Mr. Beast even reacted to it on X. Did
they literally just swap me on my
thumbnail for a red guy and get 1.8
million views? What the hell, lol?
But instead of being embarrassed, Loom
Studio seems to be so proud of it they
even put it on their website. Mr. Beast
tweeted, "We just kept going." We
confronted Loom about this and they told
us they've never reused another
creator's thumbnail. Their content is
supposedly created by their team
>> from scratch.
>> But as if all that wasn't cringey
enough, Loom Studio also offers a
coaching program. Their VIP course costs
a casual $1,499.
Included, a blueprint plus weekly calls
with our founders. We review your
channel, fix what's wrong, and push you
to your first 100K. They seem to be
pretty experienced. They say they've
built more than 100 faceless channels
and generated over 100 million views.
And we can see why. This company is run
by a team of professionals, a lion, a
wolf, and a tiger. Nothing screams men
building their AI company more than
three predator mammals with sunglasses.
[music]
The wolf conjures AI pipelines from thin
air, the one [music] who makes the
machine think, create, and scale, so
humans don't have to. Oh, how I hate
having to be a human that thinks and
creates. Finally, the wolf can make it
stop.
We dug deeper and found that Loom sits
at the center of a small network of AI
channels supporting each other. Yanni
created this map to show how these
channels are linked together.
Whenever two channels collaborated on a
video, a line connects them. True Crime
Vault pumps out fictional true crime
stories, which is just a fantastic
[music]
oxymoron. It occasionally collaborates
with other channels of the Loom network,
so we suspect it could be a client of
Loom Studio. We asked the operator via
email, but didn't receive a reply.
>> [music]
>> The channels Ego, Loom, Rocks, and Loomy
Curse are linked to the same Instagram
account of the lion Artem. [music] Just
like in nature, the lion seems to be the
real king behind this company. On Insta,
we find a profile with the same name,
Artem I, which has a link to Loom in his
profile.
Artem often posts pictures of his
vacations, for example, in Dubai. There
are luxury cars, fancy hotels, a big
yacht.
>> [music]
>> Chet, how do I say something is a fat
cliché without saying it?
>> You could try something like, "We're
wandering straight into a well-worn
narrative."
>> Okay, got it, got it, got it. Yeah,
yeah, yeah, sure. Wow, yeah, we're
wandering straight into a well-worn
narrative here.
Our research team found out that Artem
is probably from Ukraine. We found an
address in the north of the country. He
also seems to run a Ukrainian Telegram
channel about AI. In the past, he
seemingly used a different last name. Of
course, Loom are not the only ones doing
business like that. [music]
We want to dive deeper into this scene,
so we join a Discord channel.
YouTube faceless generally promotes a
kind of hustle culture. Not all of it is
about AI, but quite a big part. I've
tried doing AI-generated videos, but I
think it's just easier to steal people's
content as long as you react to the
video, aka using AI voiceover. I think
you can slow get monetized. Directly
under that comment, another user links
our fentanyl video.
Where do you get the vids from? Fern
channel. Can someone tell me how to get
Fern let me know Cypher AI voice? Hey,
anyone here in the Fern disrupt niche?
>> I feel bad for Fern and the Fern
animators, lol.
>> Why is that?
>> Cuz they spend hours animating 10 to 30
seconds of footage, and some random kid
with AI can replicate the quality.
>> But can they really replicate our
quality? We decide to take a course to
find out. We aren't ready to spend 1 and
1/2 thousand dollars to take the Alpha
Animal Coaching. Luckily, AI with Gary's
course comes at a bargain price of $75.
>> This video totally using AI-generated
video and YouTube automation. If you
already know, there's a channel [music]
called Fern, and this YouTube channel is
blowing up with cinematic 3D animations.
In their videos, they're using a lot of
mannequin figures, and it's really
effective for this kind of content. So,
if you're a beginner [music] or still
stuck on creating high-quality YouTube
content, you need Gary Studio to speed
up your workflow. You also need someone
with experience to teach and guide you
in detail. Just join my community.
>> So, using a fake identity, we join.
First, we receive an email that the
payment was successful. A few hours
later, we get another email from Gary.
He writes that we can now join school
with a monthly subscription. We thought
the $75 would unlock all materials, but
the 75 bucks is for content access. The
school community requires a separate
subscription, so both payments are
required to join.
We reluctantly pay another $67 and
finally get access. We're in and uncover
the recipe for successful and
captivating AI documentaries on YouTube.
Multiple shitty excel lists.
On top, AI with Gary provides a basic
tutorial on how to produce AI videos.
From finding your niche and choosing a
style to word-for-word prompts for
writing AI scripts or generating
animations.
So far, we just looked at the process.
But what about the results? It's a
pretty crucial aspect of edutainment
after all. How much does it eat you? We
bring in our head of fact-checking
Pascal because we do have a team of
fact-checkers who go through every
single one of our scripts and look for
mistakes. Pascal has years of experience
in investigative journalism, but now she
faces the ultimate challenge.
Sit through hours of slop and fact-check
[music] it.
We published this video on Fern in
November 2025. We sent a production crew
to Scott Payne to let him tell his
story. Just boring all human activity.
Just weeks later, this video went online
on a channel called Black Files. Only
seconds into the video, and the opening
scene is already misleading. In the
scene the video describes, the clansmen
did not wear these robes.
In this scene, the robes are incorrect.
They feature a red cross within a
circle, not just a red cross. And Pascal
suspects that this entire scene is just
made up by AI.
It directly contradicts the detailed
sources she could find. She also tried
to fact-check this video, but just
conceded. Quote, "The language is so
weird, it is hard to fact-check. Most
sentences are not proper sentences. It's
hard to follow."
And yeah, yeah, we get it.
>> Opens fire. Six bullets. Head. Seal sees
it coming. Puts head down on steering
column. Too late. Falls dead almost
instantly. Vellas runs to waiting Buick.
>> This last example might be funny because
it's bad, but factual errors and
apparent hallucinations in content
covering hate groups like the KKK are
highly problematic. We reached out to
Black Files for comment, and they
replied the channel defends its
production process, saying its videos
are created by a team using AI alongside
in-house technology and are reviewed for
accuracy and originality. They deny
copying or infringing on third-party
thumbnails, but acknowledge inaccuracies
in the video we referenced and say they
have since updated it. Anyways, we can't
help but wonder how these AI channels
cover the Holocaust. This video by Ego
reached more than half a million people.
A true historical documentary about
courage, moral failure, and one escape
that changed history forever. Let's
start with a visual highlight, prisoners
inexplicably collecting, shoveling, and
throwing a mountain of toys into a
fireplace.
We asked a Holocaust expert about this,
and she told us the scene is obviously
inaccurate. The victims' belongings,
like toys, were taken and collected, but
not piled up and burned in the
crematoria. So, someone just made this
up. Maybe the creator, maybe the AI. Who
knows?
At one point, the AI voice says,
>> By 1944, this figure was staggering.
1,750,000
victims.
And the world did not know.
That was the secret of the system's
success, secrecy, lies. No one outside
these walls knew the truth.
>> That figure of 1.75 million did
circulate for a while, and it did come
from Rudolf Vrba himself, a man who
escaped Auschwitz and whose story is
covered in this true historical
documentary. But, the video fails to
mention that it does not reflect the
current historical consensus. Today,
historians estimate that around 1.3
million people were deported to
Auschwitz between 1940 and 1945, and
around 1.1 million were murdered there.
And it's so important to be accurate
about this. Holocaust deniers often
exploit outdated or imprecise numbers to
cast doubt on the Holocaust as a whole.
That's why videos covering this should
clearly distinguish between historical
estimates made at the time and the
current academic consensus. The phrase
"the world did not know" is also very
misleading. In 1942, Allied nations had
already publicly declared that Germany
was carrying out Hitler's so-called
final solution to the Jewish question,
the mass murder of Jews. Historians also
believe many Germans had at least a
rough idea of what was happening as
information and rumors about the crimes
circulated. And last but not least, we
again again reach a full circle AI
moment when we stumble across
this scene.
>> No one had ever escaped from Auschwitz
to tell the world the truth.
>> That's incorrect, but also contradictory
to Algo's own content. The channel had
already published a video about Witold
Pilecki, another man who infiltrated and
escaped Auschwitz. We covered that story
ourselves, and Pilecki, as well as
multiple of his comrades, escaped
[music]
or bought their freedom before Werba
delivering reports about Auschwitz to
the outside world. Maybe we shouldn't
let the wolves machines do all the
thinking and creating.
>> I think [clears throat] with a lot of
these educational AI channels, the
visuals are really only half the
problem, but
a huge concern that I have is the
quality of the information in those
videos because you can be sure they're
also using AI to generate all of their
scripts.
>> There's one channel that recently got
very popular, Chloe versus History,
about a lady vlogging in the past, and
people love it. But if you actually look
at what she's saying, if you look at the
details, if you look at the whole story,
almost everything is wrong. And
especially with educational content, I
think there's this idea that people
trust the content, [music]
and they walk away being informed.
But actually, they're walking away being
less informed about certain topics, and
I think that's really bad.
>> These AI channels don't seem to care
about the quality or accuracy of their
content. Their goal seems to be simply
to publish as many videos as possible to
make as much money as possible.
Oh, and I almost forgot. We actually
spoke with a person familiar with the
production process behind Loom's
channels. They told us that they indeed
use AI and that two people had to
produce one script per day each. We
confronted Loom and sent them many
questions. In their response, they
wrote, "Half of this is totally
fictional and 30% wrong." They also told
us that their audience doesn't watch
Fern, which we are keen to believe. They
claimed that 30 people work at their
company with AI being used as a tool and
lots of manual labor still involved.
They were in disbelief of our apparent
hate of them. Lastly, life is like a
boomerang.
Okay.
>> There's no wish to make something
creative. It's just a
get-rich scheme.
>> And it's not just teenagers and Discord
channels and cool guys who keep going
even when Mr. Beast tweets driving the
slop epidemic. Various AI companies seem
to know exactly who their target
audience is and how their products are
used. Hicksfield offers a variety of
generative AI tools and recently they
uploaded this tutorial on their channel.
I used Hicksfield AI and Claw to build a
$39,500
a month faceless channel.
>> I just found a faceless YouTube channel
that's making almost $40,000 every
single month. And it made me wonder, can
I completely recreate this channel
[music] and build the exact same style
of videos using AI?
>> The 40K a month educational channel he
found is Bright Side. In case you're not
familiar with Bright Side, the
incredible irony might be lost on you.
Bright Side is one of the OG slop
factories before there was AI as we know
it. Terrible clickbait, unhinged content
pumped out every few hours.
>> It's just colorful thumbnails,
interesting clickable titles. It's
They make things.
They make things. That's about it.
>> If you've never heard of Bright Side,
good for you.
>> Bright Side
>> [music]
>> just straight-up lies or just uses these
like fear-mongering sensationalist
tactics.
>> Yet this is the type of content
Higgsfield presents as a great
opportunity to make bank with their
[music] tools.
>> Educational content appeals to everyone
and has huge audience retention, which
is exactly what drives your
monetization.
>> In this brave new world, educational
videos obviously aren't made to educate.
They're simply the most lucrative niche
to make as much money as possible. And
we can see how well that logic plays out
just a few minutes later when he uses AI
to create a video about Pompeii. We
could [music] spend minutes explaining
how much is wrong with these glass jars,
but simply put, they just didn't exist
in this form in Pompeii in 79 AD. Now,
you might wonder, who would possibly
want to slurp up this type of slop?
Well, the people at Higgsfield.
>> I think this video is very interesting.
[music] This is the kind of stuff I
watch right before going to bed.
>> Really puts the old saying that you
should make stuff you would want to
watch yourself into perspective. Next,
the tutorial demonstrates how to make
even more videos fully generated with
basically no human input.
>> Okay, one video is cool, but we need
more. So, I'm just going to type in,
"Make me two more videos." This is great
news for anyone who wants to get paid by
YouTube without actually making the
content themselves. Let's launch our
content machine that will bring in
money.
>> During a gold rush, sell shovels.
ElevenLabs offers AI voice tools, and
they have their very own tutorial on how
to make AI b-roll that's just like Fern.
And what do you do once you have your
slop visuals in place? Add a slop voice.
>> As he began his speech, there was a
shift in the room.
You could feel it. [music]
Like the start of something important.
>> During a gold rush, sell shovels. We
sent both Higgsfield and ElevenLabs a
request for comment, but didn't receive
a reply.
Let's zoom out. In the best case
scenario, these AI productions just
result in a few ridiculous visual
mistakes. Worst case, they lead to
misinformation about some of humanity's
darkest times. And how would viewers
possibly know that what they're watching
is wrong? Pascal, seasoned investigative
journalist and our of fact-checking
wrote this after reviewing some of the
videos. "It is incredibly hard to verify
things that never actually existed. Real
people usually leave some kind of trace
or reference point, but AI can just
completely make things up. If it's
already difficult for me, I don't think
average users can realistically deal
with this. After just checking half a
video, my head was genuinely spinning."
Luckily, many people instinctively
distrust AI content, [music]
but that leads to a loss of trust in
real creators, too.
>> I get comments on my videos all the time
where people think that the 3D
animations are made using AI. They think
that my voice is AI. They even think
that my face is AI generated.
>> People get so anxious about slop they
start to suspect it everywhere. If
YouTube lets this kind of content go
unchecked and allows its creators to
profit from it, in the long run, it
could damage the platform's reputation
and value proposition. So,
what is YouTube doing about it?
Already in 2025, the platform updated
its channel monetization policies. They
renamed repetitious content to
inauthentic content. Low-effort,
mass-produced uploads shouldn't make
money anymore.
And in 2026, they updated them again
with their unsatisfying or off-putting
content policy. YouTube now targets
content that feels interchangeable,
emotionally manipulative, or mimics
existing formats. Great news for us,
hopefully.
YouTube also pushed towards disclosure
and labeling. SynthID is Google
DeepMind's watermarking system. It
embeds invisible, irremovable markers
into AI-generated content. Major
generative AI companies such as OpenAI,
Nvidia, Kakao, and Eleven Labs have
adopted the watermark.
With Eleven Labs on board, more
AI-generated voices can now be
automatically detected by YouTube. In
May, the platform announced they would
start automatically tagging AI-generated
or AI-edited videos. The labels will be
clearly visible on the videos or on
shorts. The goal is to make AI content
easier to spot even if creators don't
disclose it. But of course, slop
factories will try to get around the tag
and demonetization. Hixfield has them
covered.
>> And for those of you who are worried
about AI content getting demonetized,
[music] YouTube has no problem with AI.
It just blocks people who use it to make
lazy, low-quality spam.
>> This is an unironic statement in a video
demonstrating how to automatically pump
out Bright Side style content within 20
minutes.
We also asked YouTube about slop
directly and shared our concerns. And
they actually got back to us saying that
tackling slop is a key priority for
them. They also said this, "YouTube's
approach to information quality has
always focused on promoting high-quality
content rather than fact-checking
individual videos at scale. But under
our misinformation policies, we remove
misleading or deceptive content with
serious risk of egregious harm." We do
believe YouTube understands what's at
stake and that the platform needs to
crank up the heat even further. Many
years ago, at the start of our career,
YouTube was drowning in clickbait videos
full of stock footage. That changed over
time as the platform managed to measure
and reward retention and watch time.
Deceiving viewers didn't work that well
anymore because YouTube would punish
videos when people would click off fast.
Optimizing for retention leads to its
own problems, but generative AI feels
far more threatening to overall content
quality, at least for entertainment.
This is the next thing harming the
longevity of our ecosystem.
>> [music]
>> Personally, I increasingly find myself
scrolling through my recommendations
irritated at every piece of slop served
to me. It makes me want to open the app
less, and that can't be good.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Contrary to some channels on YouTube,
our 3D animations are made by humans.
This is one of the artists who regularly
puts in countless hours in creating them
for you.
>> Hi, I'm Leonard. When I'm creating
scenes, I can easily spend the whole day
sitting at my computer. So, shout out to
FlexiSpot for sponsoring this video and
sending me this. One button and I can
switch from sitting [music] to standing.
Creating a scene like this roughly comes
down to three steps. Step one, modeling.
It's similar to the real thing. I stack
simple [music] cubes to block out the
desk, then dress the set with a plant,
computer, and the display, the usual
clutter. Step two, animating. This desk
actually moves, so I have to animate the
legs sliding into each other with a
little ease out so it doesn't feel
robotic. It's a three-stage frame, so it
adjusts to you, no matter if you're 5'2"
or 6'5".
Step three, shading. It looks a bit
bland still. I've got the white oak, but
if you want something even more premium,
they have great options for 100% solid
wood desktops. And it's not just a work
desk, [music] it can be a gaming
station, a dining table, or where all
your stuff ends up living.
Mine's basically all three, and even
when I completely load it up, it's still
really solid and stable.
>> If you want to upgrade your setup,
[music] use code fern50 for $50 off the
E7 Pro.
>> [music]
>> And if you're not sure, FlexiSpot offers
30-day risk-free returns and a 15-year
warranty. Link is in the description.